我是丹尼尔-金
我来自美国波士顿
我是一个全职数字货币顾问
我是连接两个世界的桥梁
一个是非营利，传统的，开源的
非商业性质的，基层自发的数字货币
另一个是传统的金融世界
包含了机构投资者，信托和
对数字货币感兴趣的人
这些人需要来自跟他们站在同一立场，
了解他们的专业人士的帮助
我之前的职位是股票对冲基金研究主管
我们管理者价值一亿美元的股票市场
我做了几年之后辞职单干
因为我觉得
人的一生
仅有几次能从根本上
突破自己的重要机会
我是一个博士生
在互联网泡沫期间攻读哈佛大学的博士
我记得当时我想的是
“谷歌，哇哦！”
“当时的人们都考虑要投资谷歌”
我觉得
投资一个只有20多个网站的谷歌
是个挺愚蠢的决定
为什么非要用谷歌搜索呢 --
一共也就20多个网站
你早就知道这些网站了，
值得一看的网站也就是
你收藏夹里的那20几个了
这是非常错误的想法
当比特币跟数据块链出现的时候
在认真考虑
学习了一段时间之后
我决定把所有时间投入进来
下面我想谈一下由中央银行控制的
法定通货
与比特币
比特币是第一个数字货币
从比特币白皮书出现到现在已经11年了
2008年的万圣节
门罗币像是比特币的小弟弟一样
从出现到现在也有6年了
我今天的演讲由四个部分组成
探讨一下这三种货币
其中一点是稀缺性
毕竟
物以稀为贵
所以人们是如何解决
电子货币的稀缺性的呢？
在处理稀缺性上法定货币，
比特币跟门罗币使用的方法不同
接下来我要讨论一下可替代性和隐私
今年CDC
[重要分散集群] 的
座右铭是“尊重我的隐私”
我认为我不需要
努力说服在座各位
金融隐私有多重要
换一种说法更好理解--
监管状态
也就是每个人的金融交易都被追踪
监视与调查
这不是我们想要生活的社会
接下来是社区性
每一种货币
都需要社区
需要有一群人
相信
这个货币是有价值的钱
你如果没有社区
也就没有了钱
法定通货，比特币，门罗币的背后
是由不同的社区支持的
最后是相关性
相关性这块
我要讲的是
CDC是一种
门罗币与其他加密经济群组
的合作
这次演讲
我内容着重点是
金融与经济
这又回到了对冲基金上
把法定通货，比特币与门罗比当作投资
稀缺性到底是何情况？我们为什么需要加密货币？
我们来看看我们每天使用的货币
这个是美元
人民币
欧元，瑞士法郎
我展示的是
来自政府官方的
货币流通数量的统计
这是M1
也就是纸币，货币
储蓄账户跟支票账户
所有一切现金
相关
图标上显示
自2008年十月份起，也就是比特币白皮书出世的时间
四个图表的左下角显示
这是2008年，这边是2019年底
你可以看到每个国家的
货币供应量的都有所膨胀
在短短的十一年内
美元的货币供应量上涨了2.6倍
换句话说，
印钞票的速度一直维持这个速度
我们之所以没注意到这个现象
是因为每年我们只能看到一点点的上涨
就好像是温水煮青蛙
青蛙不明白危险性
它一直待在温水里，发现后一切太迟了
已经被煮熟了
也就是
我们现在的状态
问题是
全球所有的法定通货
都在以令人不安的速度印着钞票
那什么是胜利呢？
国家货币怎样发展才算是
明智的呢？
肯定是要比其他国家膨胀的速度要慢才好
我们有如下问题
如果你缩小了看
美元的走势
近五十年的变化
你会看到呈指数增长的曲线
这是所有储户所面临的问题 --
每个有存款的人
都要面对的趋势
我们的存款一直在被
新印出来的钱所稀释
2008年是中本聪出版白皮书的一年
也就是比特币的白皮书
这个白皮书的关键是
我不会讲很多
枯燥的知识点
我猜测在座各位智商至少140
对你们来说
读一下这个白皮书，学习一下
应该不会很难
我想说的是
诺贝尔经济学奖不能颁发给无名氏
但是中本聪
是绝对可以
获得诺贝尔经济学奖的
在稀缺性方面的经济学奖
中本聪所做的是
用合成法
创造出了数字的稀缺性
不需要中央集权
来维持这种稀缺性
在所有的国家货币中
欧洲中央银行
美国联邦储备
这些中央集权政府体
决定货币供应量
现在
宏观经济理论上来说
货币供应量是会根据
社会的经济来调节的
话句话说，如果社会生产力很强
社会货币供应量就会变得膨胀
现在的问题是
国家陷入麻烦
他们负债累累
国家给人民承诺的服务
因为太过昂贵而无法实现
他们负债累累
问题是
错误的管理打破了
货币投放量与基础经济规模之间
脆弱的平衡
为社么拥有一种
不受中央委员会控制的
货币很让人激动呢
是因为它
提供给人们多一种
退出法定货币的选择
也给也给中央银行
施加了压力
让他们在将来可以做得更好一些
也许
我们将来
会遭遇几次经济危机 --
或许我们不会
再经历一次2009年的经济危机了
中本聪共识在解决稀缺性上
采取了三种方式
在账户级别
换句话说
一个人的比特币
是如何跟另外一个人的区分开的呢？
当一个人
注册了比特币账户时
他们所做的其实是选择一个号码
从256位（2的256次方）中
选择号码
人们不擅长
想象出一个很大的数字
我们现在说的是从0到10*77
也就是数字1后边有77个零
这个数字到底有多大呢？
想象一下银河系的直径
把电子
一个挨一个的
排成队
这里用的是电子经典半径
把整个银河系的直径排满电子
还不够
你还要再找
一个银河系
再把电子一个挨一个的排列
哪怕这样也不够
你再找一个
像这样的礼堂
然后让细菌一个挨一个的排满
所有这些加起来才是10的77次方的大小
你是从这么大的范围里随机挑选的数字
这也解释了为什么比特币的账户
不需要填写表格，也不需要征求账户许可
你只要选个数字
数字就是你的密匙
你需要保护它
因为只有拥有了密匙
你才可以使用个人的比特币
稀缺性的总水平是
我们如何知道在整个货币体系里到底有多比特币
以及有没有任何的损坏
稀缺性
是由一群网络矿工执行的
他们是一群很八卦的会计
从遵守一致规则中获利
最后一个问题，我们想要知道
谁给谁送了什么？
也就是区块链记录
区块链是一系列的块组成的
每个块包含了
一个人向另一个人交易的过程
谁像谁交易了多少钱
是每个块包含的内容
我们如何知道在此期间没有损坏呢？
众所周知，比特衰减
会造成损坏
也可能
有些对数据状态的错误操作
数据库是由
每个块里的矿工可改变的一小段数据段所维护的
也称作随机数
每个矿工
可以随机改变随机数，块的散列值低于一个数字
这叫做难点
通常情况下，当我们提到哈希函数时
我们不关心哈希函数的实际价值
我们只在乎哈希函数是否匹配
就好像我们检查文件完整性时
我们会把下载的文件的散列表
与你想找的文件的散列
表进行比较
在这种情况下，我们关心的是散列表的数字
数字的大小
难点是
数字必须满足每个块
换句话说，
每个块的散列表值要低于难点
用现实类比一下
想象一下你有一本会计账簿
每一页包含10分钟内发生的的交易
你要想办法
保证每一页交易的稀缺性
其中一种办法是
会计账簿的每一页质量要达到100万原子的寄倍数
每个会计师
会接触
修改这些纸张
在这个级别你可以增加或减少
万亿次的原子
纸的质量是一个随机数字
无论原子的数量是多少
很不容易
找到这样的一张纸
因为它是
包含了精确的一百万倍数的原子
而且是数字表象
你可以精准的复制它
现在你有了连锁的块
每一个快都有稀有属性
区块链把他们连接在一起
比特币与门罗币的稀有性 --
在于它们都有原代码库
在很多很多加密货币项目中
比特币很容易分离，修改
但门罗币不是这样的
门罗币是从头开始编写的
他们的椭圆曲线是不同的
这是一种技术性对冲形式
比特币的椭圆曲线值是secp256K1
而门罗币是 ed25519
我之前提到了比特币与门罗币都需要密匙
当我们要花加密货币的时候
我们需要一组数字，也就是密匙
比特币与门罗币都是这样的
不同点是
门罗币还有可视匙
这是另外一个密匙
是属于花费匙的一种
可视匙是用来解码
你个人区块链交易的
如果你有可视匙
你可以看到你涉及的区块链的交易
剩下的仍是加密的
地址空间也有所不同
比特币是10的60次方，门罗币是10的76次方
门罗币的地址空间更多
意味着如果你担心生日问题 --
生日问题是
假设有30个人
30个人中两个人生日是同一天的概率要比你想象的高很多
现在把这个问题扩展到随机选个数字
把它作为
加密账户，你会面临相同的问题
没办法保证
你随机选择的加密账户
不会被我选择了
这就是生日问题
如果我们有足够的空间，生日问题就不用过多担心
发行减缓是另一个比特币与门罗币之间的区别
比特币是阶梯式减缓
你可能听说过“减半”
比特币产量每四年
挖矿奖励就会减半
也就是在区块链里找到一页的奖励减半
每个矿工在他们的日历里
都有一个红色的日期
在那天，他们的收入减半
这就给
挖矿产业带来了很多不必要的戏剧性事件
门罗币采取的是逐渐减缓的方式
另一个不同点是
未来的货币发行量
比特币的奖励最后会趋近于0
他们预计用转账费用来弥补缺失
在门罗币，我们所关心的是：我们想要
矿工持续性地为系统工作
在门罗币里有一个叫做尾部发行
每个块永远都会有
0.6个门罗币
这笔钱是付给矿工的
来维持网络安全
长期的通货膨胀率是什么呢？
比特币基本上是0
关于比特币人们喜欢说，只会有2100百万的比特币被挖掘出来
人们很容易理解
门罗币是连续的线性增长--
但实际上并不是
像说的那样无限增长的
如果你仔细看门罗币的通货膨胀率
表面上是无限接近于0
如果你观察任何宏观经济理论
相关变量
是通货膨胀率
没人在意
名义上美元的数量会不会百亿增长
重要的是百分比
门罗币在这方面百分比很低
还在持续降低
这个曲线就是我刚才所说的 --
这些供给发行曲线显示
每种货币的存在数量与时间的函数关系
你可以看到门罗币开始时间较晚
有尾部增长
尾部增长有连续的线性斜率
造成斜率的原因是
新货币增长是给予矿工维护网络安全的奖励
然而在比特币上有一个悬而未决的问题
比特币的增长马上要达到2100万这个标记点
马上就达到0增加
有些文章提出
网络安全在那点会陷入危险
如果我们算一下这个的曲线导数--
我们对比一下去年，今年的供应增加了多少呢
换句话说，通货膨胀率是多少?
看这里
我在这里对比了几点不同
这个是金子的通货膨胀率
我们以为金子是不会通货膨胀的
不过因为有矿工--
这里说的是真正的矿工在挖掘土地
挖出金块，使世界的黄金总数增加
导致每年黄金的通货膨胀比例在1.5%左右
如果你把黄金当作货币的话
通货膨胀率不能高于1.5%
从比特币跟门罗币中我们可以看到
这个点状的蓝线显示现在
我们目前处在加密货币历史上一个很有趣的时间点
到目前为止
有很多的货币发行
为了发行这些货币
块的奖励非常高
我们现在面临新一种稀缺性
你看一下这个右边
事实上门罗币的通货膨胀率在未来的6年里
要比比特币的低（直到2025年）
有四年的时间他们膨胀率大概相同
从2029年起
比特币的通货膨胀率要低于门罗币
这里就有疑问了
矿工们如何通过维护网络得到报酬呢？
这个是中本聪共识中的重要特点
根据博弈论，所有的矿工会因为诚实而得到奖励
而不是因为贪婪而破坏游戏规则
因为挖矿工具导致的稀缺性是我们不想看到的
门罗币也有这方面的问题
在比特币的白皮书中，中本聪写到一个中央处理器一票
这也就意味着矿工得到的奖励
要与他们的付出成正比
也应该与矿工挖矿时的
花费成正比
话句话说，理论上矿工的花费与所得
应该是线性函数关系
不幸的是规模经济下硅的生产
破坏了线性关系
换句话说，如果你有2500万美金
花在新开的深圳的加工设施上
你可以自己做硅芯片
只用来做比特币的“工作量证明”
有专门的集成电路
已经用在网络与比特币上好几年了
现在来说比特币的挖掘基本上是被中国垄断了
这带来了集中性相关的担心
中国拥有所有的矿工并不需要担心
真正的问题是
这一个地区拥有全世界
几乎有所的比特币控制权
由于这个原因，出现了很多新闻
比如的中国与西方国家不断发展的贸易战
有一篇新闻文章说
中国政府近期颁布
在一年内实现
政府办公只能用中国的电脑硬件
在有限期内戴尔
或其他美国公司的电脑会被踢出中国市场
.同样的事情也发生在了中国比特币专用集成电路的加工厂
我们认为世界上的商品是自由流动的
如果只有一个地方不但控制整个世界的
所有加密散列的制造
而且因为贸易战的原因无法出口
在门罗币里，我们严肃的对待去中心化这个问题
我们对工作量证明进行了一些改动
来帮助采矿的这些人
That is, when Bitcoin started也就是当比特币被发明出来的时候
it was possible for just a regular person running
the Bitcoin client on their computer to actually have a shot
at getting a mining reward.
Those days are long gone because now
the hash power is dominated by these massive farms of ASICS.
It's just hopeless for any little guy to try to mine Bitcoin.
In Monero, we're trying to change that
and the proof of work has been modified several times.
Now, as of just last month,
the proof of work in Monero is now RandomX
which actually uses every single capability of a CPU
in doing the proof of work.
There's a basically a random program that gets executed.
Each core of the processor needs 2 gigabytes of RAM to run well.
This was a design decision made to
make it harder for botnets to control the network,
because if your computer is infected with a botnet
and 14 out of your 16 gigabytes of RAM are being eaten up,
you're probably going to notice it.
It was deliberate that design decision in RandomX to use a
high required amount of RAM for processing.
There's another source of scarcity
that is not necessarily one that you want in a blockchain,
and that is access to layer one.
Bitcoin's 1 megabyte block limit caused a project fork.
There was basically a civil war in Bitcoin over whether or not it was okay
to make blocks stay at this 1 megabyte limit.
It still rages on to this day. It's still a holy war
and this is something that Monero has avoided thus far.
Its solution to this is to use a adaptive block size
in which the maximum block size of a Monero block is flexible
and it can organically expand or shrink along with demand.
With, of course, provisions in there
to prevent the system from getting gamed.
And there's ongoing research to reduce the transaction size.
There's bulletproofs that went in recently
that reduce transaction sizes by a factor of 10, that went in.
And overnight the transaction fees for transacting Monero went down by a factor of 10
because the transaction fee is based on the kilobyte size of the transaction.
Moving on to fungibility and privacy.
Bitcoin is transparent.
If you are new to crypto you might be under the impression
that if you have Bitcoin you're anonymous.
It's this "anonymous magic internet money"
that you might have heard about.
Nothing could be further from the truth --
the popular press continues to push this misleading narrative.
Bitcoin is completely transparent
and if you read the Bitcoin white paper, it's all there.
It's specified that the sender, the receiver and how much got sent
is recorded in plaintext and recorded in the blockchain.
Which, because it has all this proof-of-work up behind it --
remember what I was saying about each transaction in the block
has a hash that makes it a very rare and unique set of data,
it's the multiple of 1 million atoms thing, right --
basically, these transparent details are written and etched into that blockchain forever.
There is no escaping that
it's completely incompatible, for example, with European privacy law, the GDPR.
Which has this "right to be forgotten"
that is totally non-existent in Bitcoin.
Once a transaction gets put into the Bitcoin blockchain it's there.
It's there forever.
And the only thing that is not
totally transparent is that the Bitcoin address
is just a hex string - it's a string.
I mean,
when you come down to it, everything's a hex string --
but the Bitcoin address is a sequence of letters and numbers that looks anonymous.
But once that gets associated to your name and face,
that association, that metadata,
that marriage between a Bitcoin account number and your identity,
that doesn't change
because the blockchain is etched in stone forever.
And it's constantly growing.
The job of the people trying to identify and "dox" everyone
is - it's just a waiting game.
You have this blockchain every day.
You get some little piece of information:
"Oh, you know, Joe in Leipzig signed up with (an) exchange".
Now their identity information is associated with this.
Basically, this metadata just kind of
continues to gather on this blockchain until you have a situation
which is actually much worse than in Fiat.
When you have a Fiat bank account you do not expect that your bank is going to post your monthly statement
up on the bulletin board outside the bank for everybody to see.
But that is exactly the situation in Bitcoin
and it's not just the people out in your neighborhood who can see it.
It's everybody. Everybody in the world can see
who sent what to who and when.
The unfortunate consequence of this, is that
Bitcoins have a history behind them.
Remember that in Bitcoin, every Bitcoin in existence
first came into being as a reward that went to a miner.
Once the miner gets that Bitcoin and then they spend it, it starts circulating in the Bitcoin economy.
But because the blockchain is transparent, it's totally "see-through".
The entire history of every single Bitcoin now in existence can be traced back
to this person all the way back to when it was mined.
It's as if you have a 10 euro banknote
and on the back of that 10 euro banknote you see a nice list showing
everyone before you who owned that.
What could possibly be the negative consequences of this?
How about innocent people getting falsely accused
because they happen to have received money from somebody who unbeknownst to them
was involved in something that was not very good.
This is happening in Bitcoin.
There's a reputation in Bitcoin that transfers as well as value
and that is what is profoundly disturbing about having this.
And I call it a surveillance coin.
In a surveillance coin, it's not just value that transmits --
it's also reputation. Which means
if you're accepting money from somebody,
you're also accepting their life history.
It's coming to you too. It's not just value.
In contrast, Monero is fungible.
Fungible just means that every unit of currency is
indistinguishable from the other units.
If I have 10 Monero, you have 10 Monero and then
we both trade the 10 Monero to other people, they still look like the 10 Monero.
There's no history. It works just like a cash bill.
It works just you think cash should work.
And it does this by adding three technologies
on top of what Bitcoin does that preserve privacy.
One is ring signatures.
In ring signatures,
the sender of funds is lined up along with 10 other senders of funds
and the only thing that you know happened in that transaction is one out of those 11 people sent money.
It's as if every time you spend money,
now you have 10 friends or 10 random people, 10 decoys
and all that you know, cryptographically, is one of the 11 have sent the money.
That protects the sender's identity.
How about the receivers identity?
Well, the receiver's Monero account does not appear unencrypted on the Monero blockchain.
A one-time-use address is what gets put on the blockchain
so that protects the recipients' privacy.
How about the amount that gets sent? Because there are
attacks that can be done by knowing,
kind of observing your pattern of how much you spend.
That is covered with technology, RingCT,
which originally was developed for Bitcoin but actually first got implemented in Monero.
RingCT stands for confidential transactions.
And all these things (are) combined to make Monero's fungibility.
The end result is that in Monero,
coins are indistinguishable from their another or they have no memory.
They have no memory of where they've been,
which is really what you want in a money because the opposite,
if you have money that has perfect memory, like it is in Bitcoin,
that unfortunately gets used to falsely associate activities of people who had nothing to do with each other.
Because Monero is fungible, users benefit by having privacy.
The Monero blockchain is public just like Bitcoin.
There is a publicly shared ledger
of who sent what to who that everybody in the world can get.
All you have to do is download the Monero software and you too
can have a copy of this ledger, of that has the complete history of who sent what to who.
The difference is that, in Monero,
the details of this blockchain are encrypted
so that if you just look at it, you see encrypted garbage.
You cannot do what you can do in Bitcoin which is
type in somebody's Bitcoin address and immediately see how much money they have.
I represent high net worth clients, institutional investors --
and for them this kind of feature is a showstopper.
Nobody with wealth wants anyone in the world to type in
their bank account and see instantly how much money they have.
Or see instantly whenever they transfer money out or get money in
as you can do in the Bitcoin blockchain.
You can set a little automated robot to like,
watch the blockchain for you and send you an alert on your cellphone
whenever a transaction goes in and out of any Bitcoin address that you choose.
This sort of kind of casual surveillance,
this invitation to be creepy on your neighbor
is something that is intrinsically part of Bitcoin.
And the deeper (it) gets into society,
the more insidious it is,
the more of a threat it is to all of our privacy.
A slander that happens is that
"okay, so you have this money that doesn't have a history,
sounds like only the criminals are going to want to use it".
It is a slander I'm kind of tired of hearing.
Monero benefits people who have nothing to hide.
The chief benefit is that
with the money that has no memory,
there's no need to worry about being falsely accused of misdeeds due
to being one hop away from a "bad person".
Basically, when you accept a surveillance coin,
you are accepting the risk that somebody unsavory will be sending you something.
For example, let's say you have a business you sell stickers or
t-shirts or something very innocent
and you decide that you're going to accept Bitcoin for your business.
Unbeknownst to you, you get a t-shirt order from a gangster
or some drug dealer or someone like that.
You had no idea they're a drug dealer, they're just sending you some Bitcoin because you're a t-shirt seller
and this is how you make money --
you need to get money from people.
But because the people watching the blockchain and putting faces and names
on addresses on blockchain, don't know that --
they can try to program that in,
but in the end, it's a probabilistic assessment of
is this bad person really related to you.
The only way that somebody finds out that they've been bitten by this is that
"oh, geez, Coinbase just emailed me and my account's been closed."
"Even the Fiat bank that I had associated with my crypto exchange"
"now thinks that there's something suspicious about me."
"Now my Fiat bank has frozen my funds for some reason" --
and it had nothing to do with anything that the person in question did.
It's just that the money itself has this
fatal flaw of being totally, (of) having a history behind it.
It's not really money,
it's like beanie babies, it's like collectables.
It's like collectible items with their own serial number that are getting passed around in this economy,
it's not a real money.
I want to leave with a Nobel Prize winning idea.
I find that not too many people have heard of this paper.
George Akerlof won the Nobel Prize in Economics for his work on asymmetric information in markets.
Anyone here know this paper well?
Okay. Great.
I'll explain it briefly.
There are two kinds of used cars.
There are lemons, which are the bad used cars.
Those are... you buy them and then they break immediately - those are lemons.
The other kind of used car is a peach - these are the good cars.
Those owners of the peaches, they did all the maintenance.
They change the oil, they did all the work to make sure that they have a nice car to sell.
Sellers know whether they're selling a lemon or a peach.
The seller knows that. If you're selling a lemon, you know it.
And you're just trying to make money off the selling of the lemon.
If you have a peach, you know it because you've been doing maintenance on that car.
However, the buyer of the car is ignorant
because both lemon sellers and peach sellers make extra sure that the paint job on the car is extra shiny.
The cars all look alike to the buyer
so the buyer knows that they are vulnerable in this situation.
The buyer knows that they could end up with a lemon.
Because the buyer is ignorant but not totally ignorant.
They are actually aware of their own ignorance.
(And) because of that, the buyer then adjusts their offer price to be slightly lower than that of a peach.
The asking, offer price for the car is going to be not quite at the peach price here.
It's going to be slightly lower.
What happens then?
If you're selling a lemon and you see this pretty high price being offered for cars, you're happy.
Because your lemon, which is worth this low price, can sell for this.
So the lemon sellers are happy.
There are more suckers out there to buy their lemons.
How about the peach sellers? The peach sellers are the ones who did the work to have a good car to sell
and now they're seeing this offer price which is less than the peach price.
They're discouraged and slightly offended
because all that work they did, all the good work that they did to keep that car good.
And they followed all the rules with their car.
That good behavior is not getting rewarded in the form of a high price coming from the buyer.
So the peach sellers get discouraged, they leave the market.
What happens is that peach sellers leave.
Well, now the buyers figure out that
their chance of buying a lemon has just gone up
and the price that they're going to offer goes down.
And you have this race to the bottom in which the offer price keeps going down, down, down.
All of the good sellers leave the market
because they are not being justly compensated for the work that they've done.
What does it have to do the cryptocurrency?
Surveillance coins
which have a total record and a total history of who had them
are the used cars of cryptocurrency.
Whenever you buy Bitcoin from somebody and you don't know the history of that Bitcoin,
you are the used car buyer in this situation.
You don't know if you accept this Bitcoin...
"Am I going to be just fine or am I going to be falsely accused of some who knows what?"
Who knows what possible crime could have been done with the person who used to own that Bitcoin.
You don't know if that's going to happen to you.
As a Bitcoin receiver, you are in the position of the used car buyer.
What in this paper is identified as
a means to avoid this race to the bottom -- is a signal.
So in the car market, for example --
and there's probably something similar to this in Europe,
where you can type in the serial number, the VIN number of a car
and then you get a report...
you can see if it's been in an accident... --
this doesn't exist in Europe? Okay, well.
Business idea for somebody...
It exists in the United States. It's called Carfax
and you type in the serial number of a car and all of its kind of past history comes up.
That information can equalize the playing field between the buyers and the sellers of cars.
This also happens in the job market.
Education is a similar situation.
If you are a boss, you're hiring a worker... you have a hundred workers out there applying for jobs.
They all look the same to you because it's like
everyone starts looking the same.
All the resumes look the same after a while.
So how are the sellers of their labor going to distinguish themselves?
They're going to have a signal.
Education is a signal just like information in the used car market is.
Basically, the sellers of labor take it upon themselves to get
educational credential to signal to the buyer of labor
that their labor is going to be worth more.
Unfortunately, what happens is that the sellers of education then figure this out
and then they just start selling education
because they know that the people coming for the education are just going
to get an employment signal.
The actual purpose of the education gets lost.
This is happening in non-fungible cryptocurrencies as well.
Right now, anybody who signs up for an account
at a centralized exchange
has to do all sorts of degrading things.
You have to hold up a picture of your ID,
you have to make a little handwritten note that says this "this is my name".
You have to basically submit all this stuff just to be deemed worthy enough
to participate in this cryptocurrency economy.
That is a signal in this sense too.
But what's interesting is that in cryptocurrency,
currently, the exchanges bear the burden of due diligence on their customers.
It's an expense for the exchanges to be doing, to check all these people out.
It could be that in the future that just like in the education market and in the car market.
It's the seller who's going to have to increasingly go through hoops
basically to prove their worthiness in this whole system.
Just to take a step back,
I've gone over scarcity in Bitcoin and Monero
and I've gone over fungibility and privacy in Bitcoin and Monero.
And if we step back,
I can identify what I think is a reason why crypto is not going to go away --
why it's here to stay.
Now we have the internet,
we have mobile telecommunication --
everybody here has at least one device
that is extremely good at copying packets.
That's what cellphones are. They are just packet copiers.
When you fetch your email,
you are copying packets from the email server to your phone to check.
We've become just extraordinarily efficient at copying ones and zeros globally.
The marginal cost of shuttling these bits around is zero.
What is rare in that world,
what is rare in a world where every human on earth basically
has the ability to copy ones and zeros anywhere around the world for free?
Well, it's going to be digital scarcity
and digital privacy.
Digital scarcity in the sense that
there's a sequence of ones and zeros that only you know
which is cryptocurrency - that's the private key.
And privacy in which you
have a sequence of ones and zeros also you only know
and that you haven't shared with everyone
like you've shared the contents of your lunch on Facebook with the entire world
and other details of your life that are basically copied around.
These are the two things that are going to be scarce in the future:
digital scarcity and digital privacy.
Cryptocurrencies offer both.
And cryptocurrencies like Monero
especially offer both because they offer privacy as well.
Next I want to talk about community.
In the past when we've had Fiat money,
basically, your nationality
told you what community you belong to for purposes of money.
If you're born in the Eurozone, well, you use Euros.
I was born American, so I use the US dollar.
That kind of gets told to you at birth
as an accident of where you were born.
Now with cryptocurrencies,
because the system of bookkeeping is a decentralized network of computers that can be worldwide
this idea of association is now fluid.
It's more open, it's really like the Reformation of the Church.
Another famous German, Martin Luther
who liberated theology from the kind of
centralized control of the Catholic Church
and liberated this ability for people to elect
to worship in the way that they chose.
A similar sort of thing is now possible, because of Nakamoto consensus,
almost 11 years and a month old.
Now it's possible for each one of us to kind of pick a group,
"pick your own church," pick your own...
like, that's not really quite right
but I think you get what I'm saying.
You can pick your own group of people who agree
on certain characteristics that they want their money to have
and you are free to associate with each of those groups.
Bitcoin is one such group that apparently doesn't
really, is not too bothered by the fact that
the currency has this perfect knowledge of history for every single coin that's out there.
And that is a large association of people all of whom have the shared belief
that the token that they are keeping track of on their blockchain is money
and there's a similar sort of community,
sort of formation that happens with the cryptocurrencies.
I'd like to share some of my observations about the Monero community
and by the way, I'm volunteering to be here.
I've paid my own dime to come out here from Boston
to kind of share what I think
my understanding of the current status of cryptocurrencies with you.
Monero is basically, it's run like a charity.
There is no company behind it.
There's no pre-mine, there's no scammy way for people to get rich.
All of the Monero in existence were given in the past to a miner
who was doing the accounting work to help support the network, just like in Bitcoin.
Both Bitcoin and Monero have the positive aspect that there's
no central company steering things to kind of make a profit.
No, it's totally open-source grassroots.
Just normal everyday people choosing to run some
peer-to-peer network software on their computer
and join this community who have this shared
ethos in what they think that money should be.
The Monero community, I find it to be idealistic scientific and yet very welcoming.
It's very chill.
There's like a lot of alpha geek happening in some other coins,
in which people are just really out there on Twitter
and they just really want everyone to know that they're the "alpha-est" geek out there.
That kind of thing is refreshingly absent in Monero.
It's very chill.
It's one thing that kind of I like about this whole vibe here at c3.
It's very chill, there's just like a lot of people lounging
and that sort of shared relaxed atmosphere is something that I've
personally observed at the Monero meetups that I've been to.
Monero Research Lab - we have full-time PhDs
who do nothing but cryptographic research.
There's sort of a pipeline of research in which
pure science gets done at Monero Research Lab.
Then, implementations of the promising idea get tested out
then there's an audit process that we actually employ --
external auditors to look at implementations of code.
Once those are clean, then we go to release.
There's this basically pipeline of technology from science to engineering
that gets pushed out in the actual release of the Monero
core software.
The LMDB database is another kind of interesting example of how far Monero has come.
In the early days of Monero,
the entire blockchain was stored in RAM
if you can believe that.
So, that kind of puts a hard limit on how big your blockchain can be
if it has to fit in RAM.
The LMDB block database - which was the brainchild of Howard Chu
who is one of the very frequent contributors
and sort of an open-source Linux guru - was added to Monero.
Monero is actually number three in terms of developer effort
if you look at the... if you rank the coins not by market cap but by actual developer effort.
It goes Bitcoin, Ethereum and then Monero.
It turns out that,
well, in my opinion,
the killer app of Nakamoto consensus is money
because you have a ledger of scarcity that's being shared.
And what's a more natural thing is there for
a shared idea of scarcity, then money?
But it turns out that money is non-trivial to get right.
It needs to be thought through.
These things like... should the money have a complete history behind it
or should it be fungible?
Like that kind of basic idea that
basic engineering design decision has to be made early on
because the technology that's needed to bake in fungibility to Monero -- it's highly non-trivial.
Monero has been added for 6 years now
and has made great improvements in that.
And the way that the social contract is,
I just can't see this happening in Bitcoin.
There are volunteer workgroups for community outreach
and, as I said before,
all of the funding to support all of this is completely 100% shaking the tin cup
and asking for people to donate out of the kindness of their hearts.
And the people in the Monero community do that.
They actually step up to the plate
and they fulfill these.
But if you look at the annual budget --
if Monero were a company, which it's not --
but if Monero were a company and you looked at its operating budget,
you would be astounded at how minuscule, how tiny it is.
And that's because you have idealistic, passionate people
working on this project in true open-source spirit,
often on their spare time.
All right.
So, just to summarize,
Monero is what Bitcoin newbs think they bought.
I'm going to switch hats a little bit.
As I mentioned, one of my jobs before going full time in crypto --
I was head of research at a hedge fund
and the question of thinking of cryptocurrency as an investment comes up.
And of course because there have been these spectacular gains in the price of Bitcoin,
it gets discussed a lot.
One thing that is positive about Monero's culture is that it is generally
gauche to talk about prices,
and returns, and the price going to the moon.
I hope that, well --
I have some background in academic finance;
there's a paper that I co-authored on the effect of liquidity on asset prices
that won a "paper of the year" award in applied finance;
and that, coupled with the Nobel Prize that I just explained --
hopefully, I can put a respectable enough academic sheen on the discussion of
the finance and economics to be forgivable by the Monero community.
But the fact is that this project is going to attract investors,
it's going to attract hodlers.
It's a socioeconomic hedge.
There are lots of investment, there are lots of ETFs out there.
If you believe that companies should be environmentally sustainable
and that their corporate boards should have official policies that
mandate sustainability in one sense or another,
there are ETFs that will only invest in those companies.
It's possible to be basically an ideological investor
if you really care about sustainability
and there's an investment for you.
If, for example, like say Islamic finance --
they are not cool with the idea of interest being paid on loans,
so you have another subset of Islamic finance investments
that don't involve paying interest on loans.
Monero - if you look at it in a similar lens - is basically an ideal hedge
for people who have two characteristics.
One is that they're concerned about mismanagement and corruption
on the part of central banks managing Fiat
and two, they're gravely disturbed by the state of surveillance capitalism
in which everything about all of us is recorded all the time
and will stay forever,
and we have little or no control over that.
It's done in the name of security
but unfortunately, if you push that line too far,
you cease to become an open and free society.
There are reasons that we, in the West, have put limits on the powers of government
and that is because of an awareness of what happens when there are no limits on the powers of government.
A project like Monero is a hedge --
it's basically a "put your money where your mouth is" kind of thing
for people who have strong feelings on those two points --
it's just going to attract investors.
Gresham's law is an economic concept that the best form of money gets hoarded.
People keep the best kind of money
and the inferior form of money, they're going to use that to spend.
But the good stuff, they're going to keep for themselves. That's Gresham's law.
So with Monero, this tends to happen.
A lot of people in Monero used to be in Bitcoin,
but now, whenever they deal with Bitcoin,
they find their heads consumed with all these worries about traceability
and so on.
It's refreshing to come to Monero
where you don't have to worry about that
because the currency is actually fungible.
And because it's fungible, it becomes a superior form of money
that gets hoarded by Gresham's law.
That's another tendency that's going to happen to people:  to want to keep the Monero
and spend the other stuff.
Also, capital gains taxes:
at least in America, and I believe in Germany too,
if you hold an asset for over a year in Germany, you don't have to pay gains on it.
That's what I've read. Is that right in Germany?  (nods)
Basically, the tax law
promotes looking at those cryptocurrency projects that are solid
and have a real reason to exist
and so that is also going to attract investment money to Monero.
The question is: can these new investors integrate into the community?
Part of what I do as a consultant is I try to bridge these worlds.
I try to take these new investors
whose inclination might be to want to talk to the "manager of Monero"
and have a word with them about the release schedule.
And they want this, and this and this feature
built into the next release --
basically, this whole mentality of
"I own some tokens therefore I'm your customer and you have to do what I say"
which of course falls completely flat on its face in any open-source project
as that's not how changes happen in Linux.
Nobody goes to Linus and demands,
makes ultimatums on what they want to see in the next rollout.
Basically, one thing that I'm doing is
trying to bridge these worlds of the traditional investment world
and that of the OG, cryptocurrency open-source world
that's surrounding us here.
Community investors,
I posit are kind of a subset of investors that
can be valued members of the community.  Instead of being
entitled and thinking that they're customers,
they'll take the attitude that they're helping to bear financial risk
on behalf of the project.
They will do things like take self-custody of their coins
and not just leave them on exchange - which lots of people do.
Lots of people leave their crypto on exchanges
then the exchange gets hacked, they lose their money.
The reality is: if the money is on the exchange,
you don't own the private key and it's not your crypto.
It's actually an IOU that you own for crypto,
it's not crypto that you own
and there's a kind of a list of aspects that I think are proper for
a community type of investor to be a solid member of the Monero community.
One thing to do, also, is to make sure that
there are proper legal structures around one's ownership of cryptocurrency.
One of the subsets of the traditional finance world that I help to bridge with cryptocurrencies is that of trusts.
In a statutory law kind of regime like Germany,
the whole concept of trust might be a little foreign
because it comes from English common law.
But the idea is that a trust is a legal entity,
it's a legal thing.
It's kind of a company
but it's a different category of legal structure.
A trust is a
kind of a holding vessel for funds that
a giver wants to give to beneficiaries but not immediately.
Basically, there are three people involved.
There's a grantor who has wealth and wants to transfer it to the beneficiaries
but not just outright, they want the money to go into a trust.
The grantor will work to make the rules of the trust
and then transfer property into the trust
as part of the document that defines the trust,
you have a list of beneficiaries who could ultimately benefit from the property
and then you have a third party which is the trustee.
The trustee is the legal owner of the assets that are given into trust
but the legal owner is with conditions.
The legal owner cannot do whatever they want with the property,
they have to follow the instructions that are in the trust document.
In effect, this is what crypto people would think of as a smart contract.
It's kind of the original old-school legal contract
and if you're careful with
which jurisdictions you place the various players in the trust,
there are advantages that can be had --
which are very dependent on jurisdiction,
and it's just completely impossible for me to spell it out
because of the complexity of this --
but possible benefits are legal tax reduction,
protection from being sued.
In other words, if money is in a trust,
it's not the giver's money anymore,
it's not the wealth owner's money anymore, it's the trus't money.
If somebody sues the wealth owner, the wealth is gone.
It's not theirs anymore, it belongs the trust.
And then there are trust laws that protect that money from lawsuits as well.
Most people think "well, you know, I'm at low risk.
I'm a nice guy I don't hurt anybody, nobody's going to sue me".
But one glaring exception to this is divorce.
People routinely get robbed by people who they only recently married
and it turns out that irrevocable trusts made before marriage --
you have to do it before or otherwise it won't count --
but it's one of the only things that can survive a challenge.
Also, legal enhanced privacy
so depending on the jurisdiction in which you place the trust,
you could benefit from enhanced privacy protecting those assets.
Actually, relevant to people who are not Americans,
you may or may not be aware of this,
but there's a saying within estate planning and wealth management
that "America is the new Switzerland."
And this is because America has laws that are asymmetric.
America has a law called FATCA, which was put in by Obama,
which requires worldwide financial institutions to send data on Americans back to the IRS.
This is why it's almost impossible for an American to get a German bank account
because the German bank account
will have a whole bunch of burdensome reporting requirements
to the IRS to take on this American customer.
That's why Americans have a lot of trouble
when they go overseas to work.
In reaction to this, the other countries of the world came up with what's called CRS
which is the "Common Reporting Standard."
The idea is the same, for example:
one European government wants to make sure that
its citizens are not trying to hide money in Australia,
so they sign this like agreement
for all these countries to share financial information with each other
to make sure that nobody's cheating on their taxes.
There's basically a bunch of countries that have signed on to this CRS
but America is not one of them.
Thus lies the asymmetry
that for US citizens who doing affairs abroad,
like legitimate businesses abroad,
all of that information gets sent back to the IRS.
But for a non-US person who sets up financial affairs in the US,
there is no obligation for the US to send the information back to the home country.
So, thus the saying, "America is the new Switzerland."
My reason for going into all that
is that Monero is a project that is important for humanity
and I think that for people who are in custody of Monero,
it's an important job for them
to basically sort this stuff out.
Figure out what's going to happen when you die
and ideally, figure that stuff out,
maybe make a trust
that kind of executes all these things while you're alive --
then you have more control over it while you're alive than when you're dead.
Basically, that's going to avoid this kind of situation where a lawsuit causes
Monero to be handed over, liquidated,
basically, things that are not good for the network --
this stuff needs to be kind of held and taken care of.
I am over time.  So unfortunately,
the section that I had on asset correlations is...
I'm just going to maybe show one slide.
This is kind of a complicated one but
this is showing the degree to which the monthly ups and downs of Monero
versus the monthly ups and downs of Bitcoin
versus the monthly ups and downs of the US stock market,
the US bond market and gold.
For example, this square here
is showing the intersection of Monero and Bitcoin.
On this axis you see the Monero return,
on this axis you see the Bitcoin return.
You can see that on months when Monero does well,
Bitcoin also tends to do well.
You have this kind of pattern, this correlation.
Here you can also see that there's some really extreme outlier months for Monero in the positive though.
This particular month, Monero basically quadrupled in one month.
This is part of owning crypto --
that you're on this really wild rollercoaster ride --
and you need to kind of be able to deal with that.
But what this is showing is that
there is a correlation between the returns of Monero and Bitcoin.
That's a .4 correlation.
A 1.00 correlation is perfectly correlated.
They go up and down together.
Negative 1 is the opposite. If one goes up, the other goes down.
In Modern Portfolio Theory --
and this is true for also your own personal portfolio, it's an idea to think about --
if you have two assets who you expect to do well in the future
and they're uncorrelated, in other words,
when one asset goes up the other is flat or maybe the other one goes down,
in other words, the ups and downs from day to day of these two different assets
tend to cancel each other out.
If you have that situation
then if you make a portfolio out of both of those assets
your combined volatility is going to be improved.
It's going to be reduced
because the components that you're adding are anti-correlated.
This is a very big deal for Wall Street investors
because it turns out correlation structure tends to be more dependable and long-lived
than predictions of outperformance, so
correlation structures tend to persist.
Wall Street is always looking for sources of uncorrelated alpha.
For example, if you look at the correlation of Monero with traditional assets like US stocks, we have 0.01.
An idea to think about is that
putting together assets that wiggle in different ways can be
a positive force for your overall portfolio.
Now again, as I mentioned, this is only talking about correlation structure.
This is like the ups and downs. This is not talking about
"is the price going to go up in the future."
That's a different question.
Let me show this and then I'll finish.
I'm sorry, I'm going over -- but I guess there's no one after me --
but I'll try to make it quick.
I think what I'm showing here is pretty much the only asset price chart you need
and that is a very long term view.
This is showing from the beginning of cryptocurrency, 2009 to 2020.
This is 11 years of history
and you almost never see this in the crypto bloggers
or people on YouTube blabbing about crypto.
They're always focused on what happened yesterday.
It's totally a distraction
for anyone who has a long term view.
So, I would suggest whenever looking at crypto as an asset, to zoom out on the horizontal scale
and also zoom out on the vertical scale.
What I'm showing here:  each of these [y axis] divisions is a factor of 10.
Here we have 1 cent, 1 dollar and 10 thousand dollars.
This is an initial investment of one euro becoming 10 million euros, that's the scale.
And on this sort of scale,
all of these ups and downs
which seem big, disappear.
For example, let's look at the S&P 500,
the US stock market.
If you're involved at all in the stock market,
you know that December 2019 has been a very good month.
We're talking 15% up
which is really big for the stock market.
But if you look on this scale, it's like a pixel.
I think this underlines the decision
that anyone has when thinking about cryptocurrency as a possible investment.
It's this baby. It's still a baby.
It's amazing because it's gone up orders of magnitude
and yet compared to other assets, it's still a baby.
This next chart shows that.
What I've done here is --
it's hard to understand if somebody tells you that the price of Bitcoin is $7,000.
It's hard to know whether that's high or low. Who knows?
It's just really hard to know
because it's just one Bitcoin
and it's hard to put that in perspective.
What I've done here is I've taken the
value of all of the Bitcoin in existence.
Starting from the beginning of Bitcoin, as time goes on,
more Bitcoins got rewarded to miners
so there have been more Bitcoins in existence
and the price has been going up and down.
I multiplied the number of Bitcoins in existence by the current price
and that gives you the market cap.
What I've done with that is I've divided that
by the value of all of the gold, above ground, in the world.
All of the gold that has been already been dug out of the ground
and is sitting in vaults around the world
and owned mostly by central governments,
but also a good amount is in jewelry, and so on,
and there are estimates of this.
Basically, there are estimates for how much gold there is in the world at any given time
so I've divided the value of all the world's Bitcoin
divided by the value of all the world's gold.
And I've done that for 11 years.
What you can see here is that,
currently, the value of all the Bitcoin in the world is about 1% of that of all the gold.
In other words, all the gold is worth a hundred times what all the Bitcoin is worth.
And if you do that for Monero --
and, arguably, this analogy is even more apt for Monero,
because when you turn a bar of gold over,
you don't see a list of everyone who owned that bar of gold,
you just see gold --
Monero acts more like actual gold than Bitcoin does,
therefore, it makes more sense to make a ratio of all the world's Monero,
how much is that worth --
divided by how much all the world's gold is worth
if you do that, we're looking at 1/100 of 1%.
That's what I mean when I say that this asset class is still a baby, it's still early.
Things could go well for it, things could go very wrong for it.
There could be a bug that nobody knows about.
There could be governmental action which a lot of people
I think overly worry about
because I think we geeks tend to think of governments as being like Reddit moderators
with ban power.
And that's not really how governments work,
it's a bit more deliberative --
and if an unjust ban happens, there are things like the Supreme Court
that might be asked to decide whether, for example,
Americans have a fundamental right to transact value in a private manner.
This could be a court case that comes up in the future
put forth by people
who really care about privacy as a fundamental human right.
I'll leave with that, and thanks for your attention.